Trimethyl glycine or TMG has been a
subject of a lot of discussion. And
although I'm late to the party, I do
have a few choice words on its true
effectiveness because across three
analyses, including up to 15 studies,
tell different stories. So, which should
we believe? Is TMG effective for fat
loss and performance or not? TMG, which
is also known as betane, is a glycine
amino acid molecule with three methyl
groups attached to it. That makes no
difference to our understanding of it,
but it makes me sound smart, so I
mentioned it. As for the useful
information, it can be created from
choline in your liver, but we tend to
create insufficient amounts. So, we get
it from our diet or supplements, too.
There's a lot to say on TMG that uh we
can't get into here, but it is believed
to play a role in several biochemical
pathways. Some related to muscle growth
and some related to fat oxidation, so
it's burning. So in brief, it alters the
gene expression in cells. It may
increase insulin like growth factor one,
so IGF-1, which is implicated in muscle
growth, and may inhibit fat cell
formation among many other mechanisms.
Again, stories for another time. The
main question here is does it work like
it's been hyped? Well, let me put these
three analyses on screen here and I'll
give you a short answer as to what these
analyses indicate as their results. No,
yes, and mostly no. So then the next
question is why the mixed results and is
there some key pieces of information
that separate when TMG is effective from
when it's not? Let's start with yes. The
researchers included six randomized
control trials. And if we pop open that
data, we're looking at body weight
measurements across five of these
studies, which are on the left side. The
weight reductions in numerical terms are
on the right side, but they're also
visually found on the forest plot as
little and big squares. The overall
result is reflected in the diamond. And
if it moves to the left of the zero line
in the middle, that indicates a
reduction in body weight from TMG
supplementation. Unfortunately, we see
there's no effect. I guess you might be
a bit puzzled because like we said at
the start with this analysis, it did
find an effect. Well, yes, body weight
doesn't change, but if we focus in on
the compartment of body weight, body
fat, we can see that there is an effect
of reducing body fat. Now the
researchers point out that TMG is known
to increase lipolysis and inhibit
lipogenesis. Essentially it encourages
fat molecule breakdown from the fat
cells and inhibits fat molecule uptake.
It does that through accentuating or
repressing the activity of key fat
enzymes that are critical for these
processes. Now let's open the analysis
that disagrees. In this analysis, the
researchers included more studies. So 12
randomized control trials. Exactly. If
we pop open the very same outcome, body
fat, note that there are five studies
included again in this specific section
of the analysis. The same rules apply
for analyzing this and the diamond
clearly overlaps the zero line. So
there's no effect. So what gives? Well,
look here. What if I told you that this
analysis included the very same studies
as the one that showed an effect? makes
it even more confusing, doesn't it? How
is it that the same input of data we get
completely different results? Well, it
comes down to using the correct
statistics. And the answer is actually
pretty obvious. You might actually be
able to see it already. Focus on the
size of the squares in the data
indicating effect. The Cholawa study has
a much bigger square than the others.
That same study doesn't get a
representative large square. The reason
for the size of the square is to show
the weight of the study. As in how much
influence does this study get on the
analysis, which is also represented on
the far right. The Cholaw West study
sucks up 68% of the influence in one
analysis and a mere 10% in another. So,
who's right? Well, technically sort of
both are wrong. I know, even more
complexity. Now, don't worry. I'll keep
the uh rest of this quick so we can get
to the performance aspects of TMG. When
there's a lot of different results in a
meta analysis, that's called interstudy
heterogeneity. Usually in such a case,
there's a statistical model that's used
to account for that uncertainty by
reducing the emphasis of any one study,
muting the whole analysis. That's
technically what this analysis did. So,
it would seem like they did things
correctly, but there's also no detected
heterogeneity. So, a random effects
model is generally not the correct
statistical test to use. I'm sure
dedicated statistitians could make more
detailed arguments, but for our
purposes, it's slightly incorrect. So,
you care about who's right. And in
short, the analysis applying less weight
to the studies is more correct in my
mind for reasons that I mentioned,
including some others that I won't tire
you with. Hey, hey, wake
up. Briefly, that means that TMG
supplementation is more likely
ineffective for fat loss than effective,
at least based on the data that we have
here. But is it a different story for
muscle performance? And are we possibly
missing a link to this all? Well, let's
discuss. As soon as I mention that, I go
over more on the mechanisms and details
of TMG, as well as some other TMG data
in the extended version of this video
that your eyeballs are sensing right
now. If you're interested in access to
that full analysis along with access to
all my other work delivered to you
weekly in video and written form along
with a monthly podcast and community
live streams with me, be sure to check
out the Physionic Insiders right in that
description box. Hope to see you there.
For muscle performance, we can rely on
this third analysis wherein the
researchers pulled 15 studies into
another meta analysis. However, this
time they focused on muscle performance.
The same rules apply, but now we're
looking at muscle strength split by
upper body and lower body. There's
individual overall effects diamonds for
each subgroup. If they move to the
right, there's an increase in muscle
strength. Now, while the upper body
strength measure might seem like it's in
favor of TMG, remember also called
butane, it didn't reach statistical
significance, indicating no detected
effect. However, when looking at lower
body strength measures, we do see an
effect in favor of TMG supplementation.
So, these data would indicate that TMG
may be worthwhile when trying to improve
muscle strength, especially in the lower
body, even if not in the upper body.
Okay. mixed results in the two metrics
that we covered. But assuming that you
wanted to have these benefits or you
still believe that TMG helps with fat
loss, what are some sources? Well,
standardized to 100 g, some good sources
are wheat, spinach, but there's also
some found in a turkey and shrimp at
lower concentrations. Or as these
studies are looking at TMG directly
without other molecules in the mix, the
most direct path might be
supplementation. Still, is there a
missing link with TMG supplementation? I
think so. It seems to me that TMG is
likely most effective, if effective at
all otherwise, if paired with exercise,
especially resistance training. The
majority of the studies included in all
of these analyses included people who
were at least physically active, but
many were in resistance training
individuals. This offers a clue that we
should probably pair them. That all
said, after dunking you unwillingly in a
vat of statistics, what's the short of
it? On the outcome of I feel like a
judge in a courtroom. On the outcome of
fat loss, the jury finds TMG guilty of
not working. On the other hand, when
paired with resistance training and
possibly exercise as a whole, TMG is
moderately effective at improving muscle
strength. If you should use it or not
is, as always, a personal choice. But if
you don't exercise, I'd save your money
in relation to these outcomes.
Otherwise, it will be worth it for those
who care about maximizing performance.
But let's be real, when discussing
performance, there are alternatives like
this one or this one. Thanks for
watching.